Guide to the Western Wood Products Association Records 1909-1970
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Western Wood Products Association Records
1909-1970
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library
Mss 1336
Western Wood Products Association
60 linear ft. 40 document cases; 28 record cartons; 3 boxes Oversize A—11x14; 6 boxes Oversize B-1—16x20
Records primarily document the activities and history of the West Coast Lumbermen's Association (WCLA), a lumber industry trade association which was incorporated in 1911 and was succeeded in 1964 by the Western Wood Products Association. The WCLA's territory extended throughout the Douglas fir region of western Oregon and Washington and also included northern California. The records (1909-1970) include accounting information, biographical and historical materials, correspondence, meeting minutes, membership lists, newsletters, press releases, promotional materials, scrapbooks, and statistical information.
Historical Note
The West Coast Lumber Manufacturers Association was incorporated in 1911 in Centralia, Wash., with the merger of the Pacific Coast Lumber Manufacturers Association, the Southwest Washington Lumber Manufacturers Association, and the Oregon and Washington Lumber Manufacturers Association. The new trade association, headquartered in Tacoma, Wash., represented the Douglas fir industry, then centered in western Washington. By 1916 the organization had become the West Coast Lumbermen's Assocation (WCLA), and its offices moved to Seattle, Wash.
By the 1920s, the WCLA had become an important representative for manufacturers of Douglas fir, West Coast hemlock, Western red cedar, and Sitka spruce wood products. In 1928, Colonel William B. Greeley, former chief of the U.S. Forest Service, became the Secretary-Manager of the organization. His reforms brought loggers, wood preservation plants, mill-work plants and other related branches of the industry together into a stronger association. During the 1920s and 1930s, the center of lumber production gradually shifted from Washington to Oregon, and in 1946 the WCLA transferred its headquarters to Portland, Or.
The WCLA was incorporated under the laws of Washington as a stock corporation, with member companies each holding one share. Membership in the association was entirely voluntary. For decades the association was supported by dues assessed on logs and/or lumber produced by member companies. In 1949, the WCLA dues structure was changed to one based solely on lumber production.
The WCLA provided many services to its member companies, one of the most important being the rationalization of the largely chaotic West Coast lumber industry during the 1910s and 1920s. As the industry evolved, the association's activities became more sophisticated, and by the 1950s the WCLA supported its members in many ways. The Traffic Department negotiated with railroad, trucking and shipping lines for favorable freight rates. The Statistical Department produced regular reports about conditions within the West Coast lumber industry. The Accounting Service assisted member companies with accounting, cost analysis, and taxation problems. The Promotion Department produced literature and advertising publications, newspaper and radio spots, motion pictures, and a membership directory to market the products of the West Coast lumber industry. The Technical Service Department, staffed by engineers, conducted research to develop new and improved uses for West Coast lumber products and produced publications such as the Douglas Fir Use Book. The Public Relations Department produced stories and news releases about the positive impact of the lumber industry on the economy of the Pacific Northwest and attempted to counter negative publicity. James Stevens, Public Relations Counsel of the WCLA and author of stories about the legend of Paul Bunyan, produced hundreds of issues of Out of the Woods, a newspaper column about conditions within the industry. The Educational Program Department, which was closely related to Public Relations, provided literature, slides, filmstrips and motion pictures to schools.
The WCLA worked closely with the National Lumber Manufacturers Association (NLMA) and other regional and national organizations to advance the interests of the lumber industry. The West Coast Lumber Inspection Bureau (WCLIB), a separate but closely allied organization to the WCLA, established standard lumber grading rules, maintained uniform grades, trained and supervisied mill graders, licensed mills to use official grade stamps, and issued Certificates of Inspection when requested. The WCLIB concentrated on rail and truck shipments in the domestic and export markets. Another closely allied organization, the Industrial Forestry Association (IFA), promoted forest conservation practices through educational and public relations activities and served as the certifying agency of the tree farm program in the Douglas fir region of western Oregon and western Washington.
By the early 1960s, business leaders determined that a stronger regional association was needed in the face of growing national and international competition in the lumber industry. In 1964, the West Coast Lumbermen's Association merged with the Western Pine Association (WPA), a trade association which represented lumber interests east of the Cascade Mountains in Oregon, Washington and California. A new organization, the Western Wood Products Association (WWPA), was formed from this union, and in 1969 the WCLA was dissolved as a corporation.
Records documenting the activities and history of the West Coast Lumbermen's Association (WCLA) include accounting information, biographical and historical materials, correspondence, meeting minutes, membership lists, newsletters, press releases, promotional materials, scrapbooks, and statistical information. The collection includes biographical information about several principal members of the association, including Colonel William B. Greeley, Arthur W. Priaulx, Harold V. Simpson, and James Stevens. Board of Trustees and committee meeting minutes provide a comprehensive overview of the activities and inner workings of the organization. The Barometer, a weekly report prepared by the Statistical Department, provides information on lumber production, orders, shipments, gross stocks, unfilled orders, and operating mills.
The records include many examples of promotional materials, from pamphlets and booklets to color magazine advertisements for houses constructed of West Coast lumber. Many of the promotional items were produced from the 1940s through the early 1960s during the post-World War II housing boom. Promotional materials also include the membership directory, Where to Buy West Coast Lumber, which lists names and addresses of all member mills, managers and sales managers, facilities, species cut, and items and specialties manufactured.
The collection includes information about the West Coast lumber industry during the Great Depression, particularly meeting minutes concerning the WCLA's adoption and enforcement of lumber codes imposed by the National Recovery Administration (NRA) in 1933. The records also document the Pacific Northwest lumber industry's contributions during World War II and the Association's public relations efforts on behalf of the "Keep Oregon Green" and "Keep Washington Green" programs for preventing forest fires, a movement which began in the early 1940s. The collection contains materials, including annual reports, meeting minutes, and statistics, from other related organizations, such as the Industrial Forestry Association (IFA), the West Coast Lumber Inspection Bureau (WCLIB), and the Western Pine Association (WPA).
The collection is arranged into two subgroups:
Subgroup 1: West Coast Lumbermen's Association Records, 1909-1970
Subgroup 2: Western Wood Products Assocation Records
Subgroup 2 currently includes a small quantity of unprocessed records and audio recordings. This sub-group will be processed as more materials from the Western Wood Products Association are deposited in the future.
Subgroup 1 is arranged into three series:
Series A: Governance and Membership Records, 1911-1970
Series B: Departments and Functions, 1909-1967
Series C: Branches and Associated Organizations, 1911-1965
The collection is open to the public. Several folders in the Accounting/Finance Subseries contain personal employee information and are restricted until 2060.
Gift of the Western Wood Products Association, 1971, 1975 and 1997 (Accession nos. 11791, 13278 and 23494).
Additional records from the Western Wood Products Association will be added to the collection in the future.
Photographs have been separated into the Western Wood Products Association Photographs Collection, Organized Lot 208, at the Oregon Historical Society Research Library. A guide to this collection will be completed in the future.
Motion picture films have been separated into the Western Wood Products Association Collection in the Oregon Historical Society Research Library Moving Image Collection. A guide to this collection will be completed in the future.
Lucia, Ellis. Head Rig: Story of the West Coast Lumber Industry. Portland, Or.: Overland West Press, 1965.
The Timberman Magazine Photographs Collection (Org. Lot 351), Oregon Historical Society Research Library. This monthly magazine (Research Library Serials Collection) covered all aspects of the timber industry, including logging operations, forestry practices, transportation, lumber production, and wood product manufacture.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Greeley, William Buckhout, 1879-1955; Priaulx, Arthur W.; Simpson, Harold V.; Stevens, James, 1892-1971
Industrial Forestry Association (U.S.); National Lumber Manufacturers Association; West Coast Bureau of Lumber Grades and Inspection; West Coast Lumbermen's Association; Western Pine Association
Douglas fir --Pacific states; Forests and forestry --Pacific states; Forest products --Pacific states; Lumber --Pacific states; Lumber trade; Sitka spruce --Pacific states; Timber --Pacific states; Trade associations; Tree farms --Pacific states; Western hemlock --Pacific states; Western redcedar --Pacific states; Wood products
Business records; Scrapbooks
Oregon; Portland; Seattle; Washington (State); Business, Industry, and Labor; Forestry and Forest Products; Logging
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- West Coast Lumbermen's Association Records, 1909-1970; Subgroup 1; 60 linear ft. (40 document cases; 28 record cartons; 3 boxes Oversize A—11x14; 6 boxes Oversize B-1—16x20)
  The records provide a comprehensive overview of the activities, functions, history and membership of the West Coast Lumbermen's Association (WCLA). The sub-group also contains information that documents some of the history of its predecessors. Series A contains governance and membership records, and Series B contains records from departments within the organization. Some records of several branches and associated organizations are included in Series C. The records include accounting information, biographical and historical materials, correspondence, meeting minutes, membership lists, newsletters, press releases, promotional materials, scrapbooks, and statistical information.
  - Governance and Membership Records, 1911-1970; Series A
    The series is arranged into 12 subseries based on the activities that occurred at the administrative and membership levels of the West Coast Lumbermen's Association.
    Records within each subseries are arranged by subject if necessary, and then alphabetically and chronologically by folder.
    - Biographies and Histories, circa 1913-1970; Subseries 1
      The subseries includes an address about the history and functions of the organization, The West Coast Lumbermen's Association: Its Purpose, History and Activities. It also contains information about several principal members of the WCLA and their activities within the organization and the Pacific Northwest lumber industry. From 1911 to 1916, the WCLA was known as the West Coast Lumber Manufacturers Association.
      - Biographical Sketches—information about significant members of the Pacific Northwest lumber industry, 1946-1948; 1955-1956; 1964-1965 (Box-folder 1/1)
      - Brown, Ralph D., Assistant Secretary-Manager—correspondence related to his retirement from the WCLA, 1953 (Box-folder 1/2)
      - Gerlinger, George T., member, WCLA Board of Directors—memorials and press releases, 1945; 1948-1949; 1955 (Box-folder 1/3)
      - Greeley, William B., Secretary-Manager and Vice President—articles, biographical information and press releases, 1945-1946; 1949-1950; 1954-1955; 1960 (Box-folder 1/4)
      - Simpson, Harold V., Executive Vice President—biographical information, 1945; 1955; 1961-1963 (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Stevens, James, Public Relations Counsel—articles, biographical information and correspondence, 1937; circa 1939; 1940-1942; 1945; 1948; 1950-1953; 1957-1958; 1965 (Box-folder 1/6)
      - Historical Material, circa 1913; 1930-1932; 1934; 1944-1948; 1950-1954; 1958-1961 (Box-folder 1/7-8)
        Folder 1/7 contains an address, The West Coast Lumbermen's Association: Its Purpose, History and Activities, given by Arthur K. Roberts, Education Director, in 1949. The folder also contains an early history of the Pacific Coast Lumber Manufacturers Association and the West Coast Lumber Manufacturers Association, as well as correspondence and articles about the history of the WCLA.
      - Historical Reference Information, 1928-1930; 1932; 1935-1937; circa 1940; 1944-1945; 1949; 1963 (Box-folder 1/9)
        Information about the development of the WCLA's programs and descriptions of some of the services offered by the organization.
      - Cargo mills that have gone out of business—correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Logging and Sawmilling History, 1948; 1950; 1954; 1970 (Box-folder 1/11)
        Articles and information about developments in the lumber industry, particularly technological advances.
      - Lumber History—general, 1917; 1926; circa 1928; 1940; 1942; 1945; 1948; circa 1950; 1951-1955; 1957; 1959; 1969 (Box-folder 2/1-3)
        Articles, addresses and reports which describe developments and activities within the lumber industry of North America and other regions of the world.
    - Office Administration, 1938-1964; Subseries 2
      Information about the daily operations of the central office of the WCLA and background information about the WCLA and West Coast Lumber Inspection Bureau (WCLIB).
      - Office Procedures, 1948; 1950-1955; 1957-1962 (Box-folder 2/4)
      - Staff Meetings—minutes, 1938 (Box-folder 2/5)
      - WCLA and WCLIB Background Information, 1941; 1953; 1957-1964 (Box-folder 2/6-8)
        By-laws, correspondence, membership information, membership lists, reports, and a booklet, Where to Buy West Coast Lumber.
    - Membership Directories and Meeting Programs, 1919-1964; Subseries 3
      - Membership Directories and Lists, 1919-1922; 1924-1930; 1933; 1935-1938; 1942-1948 (Box-folder 2/9, Box-folder 3/1)
      - Annual Directories, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 3/2)
      - Meeting Programs, 1922-1925; 1936; 1939-1964 (Box-folder 3/3-5)
    - Annual Membership Meetings, 1924-1968; Subseries 4
      Annual membership meetings were held in various cities of the Pacific Northwest to report on the lumber industry's development and to determine and revise the WCLA's policies.
      - Annual Meetings—articles and minutes, 1924-1925; 1928; 1930 (Box-folder 3/6)
      - Annual Meetings—minutes, 1929-1945; 1946-1960; 1964-1965; 1968 (Box 41, Box 42)
        Boxes 41 and 42 contain minutes that have been bound into volumes.
      - Annual Meetings—addresses, minutes and press releases, 1936-1949 (Box-folder 3/7-8)
      - Annual Meetings—address, circulars and minutes, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 3/9)
      - Annual Meeting—addresses and minutes, 1953 (Box-folder 4/1)
      - Annual Meeting—circulars, correspondence and minutes, 1955 (Box-folder 4/2)
      - Annual Meetings—brochures, correspondence and press releases, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 4/3)
      - Annual Meeting—correspondence, 1959 (Box-folder 4/4)
      - Annual Meeting—correspondence, proxies and resolution, 1960 (Box-folder 4/5)
      - Annual Meetings—correspondence and minutes, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 4/6-8)
      - Annual Meeting—correspondence, minutes, press releases and reports, 1963 (Box-folder 4/9-10, Box-folder 5/1)
      - Annual Meetings—correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 5/2)
      - Annual Meeting—minutes, 1964 (Box-folder 5/3)
      - Annual Meetings—correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 5/4)
      - Annual Meeting—minutes, 1965 (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Membership Meetings, 1913-1933; 1957-1960; Subseries 5
      Membership meetings were held in various cities of the Pacific Northwest and appear to have been conducted more regularly during the early years of the WCLA.
      - Minutes, 1913-1918; 1928-1933 (Box 41)
        Box 41 contains minutes that have been bound into volumes.
      - Meeting, Seattle, Wash.—address by Major David T. Mason, 1920 (Box-folder 5/6)
      - Minutes, 1922-1924 (Box-folder 5/7)
      - Meeting, Aberdeen, Wash.—minutes, 1924 (Box-folder 5/8)
      - Meetings, Tacoma, Wash.—minutes, 1924-1925 (Box-folder 5/9-10)
      - Meeting, Seattle, Wash.—minutes, 1925 (Box-folder 6/1)
      - Meeting, Portland, Or.—minutes, 1925 (Box-folder 6/2)
      - Meeting, Hoquiam, Wash.—minutes, 1925 (Box-folder 6/3)
      - Meeting, Tacoma, Wash.—minutes, 1925 (Box-folder 6/4-5)
      - Meeting, Portland, Or.—minutes, 1926 (Box-folder 6/6)
      - Meetings, Portland, Or.—minutes, 1957; 1960 (Box-folder 6/7)
    - Annual Reports, 1911-1956; Subseries 6
      Annual reports were produced for the membership of the WCLA and other interested parties. From 1911 to 1916, the WCLA was known as the West Coast Lumber Manufacturers Association.
      - Annual Reports, 1911-1913; 1915-1929; 1946; 1926-1938; 1939-1956 (Box-folder 6/8-9, Box 42, Box 43)
        Reports in Boxes 42 and 43 have been bound into volumes.
    - Board of Trustees/Directors, 1911-1969; Subseries 7
      Includes meeting minutes, information about board elections, and lists of members. The subseries also contains minutes about the dissolution of the WCLA and its merger with the Western Pine Association to form the Western Wood Products Association.
      - Board of Trustees Elections, 1958-1964 (Box-folder 6/10, Box-folder 7/1-4)
      - Board of Trustees/Directors, District Trustees, Committees, and Officers—member lists and correspondence, 1926-1927; 1929-1930; 1932-1966 (Box-folder 7/5-7)
      - Board of Trustees and Committee Assignments—member lists and correspondence, 1963 (Box-folder 7/8-9)
      - District Meetings—lists of companies and individuals, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 8/1)
      - Board of Directors/Trustees—index of minutes, 1951-1960 (Box-folder 8/2)
      - Meeting Schedule and Agenda, 1963 (Box-folder 8/3)
      - Board of Trustees, West Coast Lumber Manufacturers' Association—minutes, 1911-1916 (Box 41)
        The WCLA was known as the West Coast Lumber Manufacturers Association from 1911 to 1916. The Articles of Incorporation are included at the beginning of the 1911 minutes. Minutes in Box 41 have been bound into volumes.
      - Board of Trustees/Directors—minutes, 1916-1925; 1927-1945; 1946-1960; 1964-1968 (Box 41, Box 42)
      - Board of Trustees—NRA Lumber Code minutes, 1933-1936 (Box-folder 8/4-5)
      - Board of Trustees/Directors—minutes, 1928; 1957; 1959-1962 (Box-folder 8/6)
      - Board of Trustees/Directors—correspondence and minutes, 1960 (Box-folder 8/7)
      - Board of Trustees—correspondence and minutes, 1961 (Box-folder 8/8, Box-folder 9/1)
      - Board of Trustees—minutes, agendas, correspondence and reports, 1962 (Box-folder 9/2-3)
      - Board of Trustees—minutes, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 9/4-6)
      - Board of Trustees—correspondence and meeting agendas, 1963 (Box-folder 10/1)
      - Board of Trustees—materials for meeting, 1963 (Box-folder 10/2)
      - Board of Trustees—minutes, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 10/3)
      - Board of Trustees—correspondence and reports, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 10/4)
      - Dissolution of WCLA—circulars, minutes and member lists, 1964-1969 (Box-folder 10/5)
      - WCLA Merger—industry organizations, 1961-1964 (Box-folder 10/6)
    - Accounting/Finance, 1929-1970; Subseries 8
      Folders 11/5-7 contain personal employee information and are restricted until 2060.
      - Annual Budget, 1929 (Box-folder 10/7)
      - Annual Report of Finances, 1948; 1959-1963 (Box-folder 10/8-10, Box-folder 11/1-3)
      - Cash Disbursements Ledgers, 1964-1966; circa 1970 (Box-folder 72/1-4)
      - Cash Receipts and Charges Ledger, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 72/5-6, Box-folder 73/1)
      - Employees' Retirement Plan, 1958; 1961 (Box-folder 11/4)
      - Employees' Retirement Plan, 1955-1957 (Box-folder 11/5-6)
        Folders include personal information. Access restricted until 2060.
      - Employees' Retirement Plan—applications, 1956-1960 (Box-folder 11/7)
        Folder includes personal information. Access restricted until 2060.
      - Employees' Retirement Plan, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 12/1-2)
      - Employees' Retirement Plan—trust agreement, 1956 (Box-folder 12/3-5)
      - General Accounts Journal, 1932-1939 (Box-folder 73/2-3)
      - General Accounts Ledgers, 1950-1971 (Box-folder 69/1-5, Box-folder 70/1-4, Box-folder 71/1-4)
      - Office Furniture and Equipment Depreciation Ledger, circa 1945; 1949-1964; 1968; 1970 (Box-folder 13/1-5)
      - Report of Audit, 1930 (Box-folder 13/6)
      - Trustee Account Ledger, 1956-1967 (Box-folder 73/4-6)
    - Circulars, Newsletters, News Releases and Reports, 1920-1964; Subseries 9
      Includes the News Letter, Progress Report, and Vice President Reports which were produced by the WCLA's central office and served as a primary method of communication to the membership and other interested parties. The materials contained in boxes 43-59 have been bound into volumes.
      - Circulars—numbered, 1920-1923; 1923-1928; 1929-1931; 1931-1935; 1935-1937; 1937-1939; 1940-1941; 1941-1943; 1943-1944; 1944-1947; 1947-1950; 1951-1955; 1956-1961; 1962-1963; 1959-1964 (Box 43, Box 44, Box 45, Box 46, Box 47, Box 48, Box 49, Box 50, Box 51, Box 52, Box 53, Box 54, Box 55, Box 56, Box-folder 13/7)
      - Circulars—unnumbered, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 13/8-9, Box-folder 14/1-2)
      - Circulars for West Coast Forest Products Bureau—numbered, 1921-1925 (Box 59)
      - WCLA News Letter, 1930-1932; 1934-1935; 1929-1932 (Box-folder 14/3, Box 56)
      - WCLA News Releases, 1963; 1958-1961; 1929-1931; 1962; 1932-1942; 1943-1952; 1953-1957 (Box-folder 14/4, Box 55, Box 56, Box 57, Box 58, Box 59)
      - WCLA and WWPA News Releases, 1964 (Box-folder 14/5)
      - WCLA Progress Report, 1963 (Box-folder 14/6)
      - Vice President Reports, 1948-1950; 1951-1955; 1956-1961; 1962; 1963 (Box 53, Box 54, Box 55, Box 56, Box-folder 14/6)
    - Government and Industry Relations, 1915-1965; 1915-1936; Subseries 10
      Contains correspondence, meeting minutes and reports that address issues concerning the lumber industry, particularly lumber standards and government regulations. An industry newsletter concerning the NRA Lumber Code, the West Coast Lumber Code Bulletin, is included.
      - Central Committee on Lumber Standards—meeting reports, 1922-1923 (Box-folder 15/1-2)
      - Central Committee and Consulting Committees on Lumber Standards—joint meeting report, 1922 (Box-folder 15/3)